[Music]
welcome to photo theology the podcast
where you learn how to see the Bible
with new eyes
I'm your host pastor Idol Myers and I'll
be sharing with you a very special
method of how to more effectively study
the Word of God
[Music]
if you enjoy the podcast please consider
supporting our ministry at patreon.com
forward slash power of the land that's
patreon.com/lenguin
[Music]
all right let's get to it episode 1
photo biology so we have the story in
the Bible of Elijah and Elijah you can
read about it in second Kings chapter 2
and in this story Elijah is about to be
taken off the scene he's about to be
caught up by a chariot of fire into the
heavens so he and Elijah are walking
there at the Jordan and Elijah said to
Elisha ask what I shall do for thee
before I be taken away from me and
Elisha said I pray thee let a double
portion of thy spirit be upon me Elisha
is asking for a double portion of
Elijah's spirit the disciples of Elisha
are standing on the banks and they're
watching this event unfold when suddenly
chariots of fire come down out of the
heavens to catch Elijah up to the
heavens Elisha is left standing there
but he has now been blessed with a
double portion of Elijah's spirit the
disciples of Elisha go on to follow
Elijah there's a transition of power
from Elijah to Elisha at the Jordan in
2nd Kings chapter 2 that very same
chapter the first miracle that Elisha
performs after he leaves the Jordan is
that he heals water so that the people
of this particular City can drink it
photo theology what is it it is a study
of the Word of God through the use of
pictures so let me explain when I was
little I used to play this game called
concentration and in this game you had
all of the cards of the deck facing down
you would turn a card and then you would
turn another card trying to find a match
and as the game went on you had to
remember where you saw that picture
before where you saw that card before it
would help you to find the match so it
was a game of concentration a game of
memory
well Bible study is just like that
it is the comparison of the different
pictures of the Bible when you find a
match that's when you experience that
moment of excitement that moment of joy
you see as you guys were listening to
the story I just shared the story of
Elijah and Elijah some of you maybe not
all of you but some of you may have
begun thinking wait a minute I've heard
something like this before I've seen
seen that picture before so if you
started to think about Jesus and John
the Baptist you have just experienced
photo theology you see just as there was
a transition of power from Elijah to
Elijah at the Jordan so there was a
transition of power from John the
Baptist to Jesus at the Jordan and just
as Elijah was more powerful than Elijah
remember John the Baptist himself said I
must decrease that he may increase
speaking of Jesus
just as Elijah was taken off the scene
after this transition of power so John
the Baptist was taken off the scene
after their transition of power you'll
remember that the disciples of Elijah
went on to follow Elijah just as the
disciples of John the Baptist went on to
follow Jesus in fact the Bible tells us
that Jesus himself said of John the
Baptist that he was Elijah in a few
eleven Jesus actually like in John the
Baptist to Elijah
so here's a question if John the Baptist
was a type of Elijah then who was Elijah
and you begin to see the picture come
together
you see Elijah would have been a type of
Jesus Christ now I want you to think
about this
the Bible is full of images that point
us to the gospel and in order for us to
begin to see the picture we have to
learn how to read the Bible in pictures
you've heard the saying a picture is
worth a thousand words I want you to
start approaching the Bible as God's
picture book when you read the Bible I
want you to see not just the words but I
want you to see the pictures so imagine
it like this in your mind is a Hall and
let's call that Hall memories Hall and
every time you read a story in the Bible
I want you to hang that picture in
memories Hall because what's gonna
happen is that as you're reading other
parts of the scripture and as you're
reading other stories you're going to
begin to see similarities between the
story you're reading and the pictures
that you have hanging on memories Hall
and what will happen is you'll you'll
run down memories Hall and say wait a
minute wait a minute I've seen that
picture somewhere before and before you
know it you have one of those aha
moments where you see something in the
scripture that you've never seen before
Bible study is the bringing together of
the pictures of Scripture to form a
beautiful tapestry after all I want you
to think about it God is an artist he's
a creator and that's how he put the
Bible together train your eyes to begin
to see the pictures of the scriptures
let me talk to you just for a moment
about attitude in Luke 5 verse 3 the
Bible says speaking of Jesus he entered
into one of the ships which was Simons
and prayed him that he would thrust out
a little from the land
and he sat down and taught the people
out of the ship now when he had left
speaking he said unto Simon launch out
into the deep and let down your nets for
a draught Simon answered said unto Him
master we've told all night and have
taken nothing nevertheless at thy word I
will let down the next and when they had
done this they enclosed a great
multitude of fishes and their nets
break I want you to see that story and I
want you to understand that for many of
us we are afraid of launching out into
the deep of the Scriptures we stay by
the shores we stay by what we have heard
other people say and we we don't go out
any further because because of fear
Jesus himself says launch out into the
deep because when you launch out into
the deep and let down your nets I'm
going to bring you a multitude of fish
I'm gonna bring you a find so huge a
find so amazing that is gonna break your
nets
that's how Bible study ought to be when
you take your net every day you cast it
out into the deep and you say Lord open
my eyes help me to see that which I have
not seen before and the promise is that
your net will break you will be excited
about what you see
in the Word of God you'll be excited
about what you find in the deep so
listen the ocean is beautiful on the
surface it it's magnificent when you see
the Sun just shining down and the light
glimmering off of the waters but as
beautiful as it is on the surface the
true beauty of the ocean is beneath the
surface and the deeper you go is the
more beautiful the ocean gets that is
much like how many of us approach the
scriptures we enjoy the surface we stay
on the surface fearful or maybe even
thinking that we can't go into the deep
you know I'm not trained enough to
understand the deep but I've never been
in the deep before and and you know I'm
not a scholar or or I don't have the
kind of training that would allow me to
catch anything in the deep what that is
allowed because with God on your side
with the master telling you launch out
into the deep he's going to be there to
help you look you see what Simon
responded we've toiled all night and
have taken nothing how many of us
approach the scripture and kind of throw
our hands up because we're saying you
know what we have toiled and toil that
is we haven't worked and worked at this
I have tried to study the Bible in
different ways and I can't find anything
I don't want to launch out into the deep
I don't want to let my neck down anymore
just let the pastor feed me
just let the fit the pastor provide my
fish
and we love it let me tell you just like
Simon obeyed the word of the Lord and
said okay I'm gonna launch out into the
deep I want you to approach the
scriptures that same way you see
attitude is everything
if you go out expecting that the Masters
word will be fulfilled you're gonna
catch fish your net is gonna break I
promise you God promises you forget
about my promises matthew 7:7 this is
what jesus says ask and it shall be
given you seek and you shall find knock
and it shall be opened unto you for
every one that asketh receiveth and he
that seeketh findeth and to him that
knocketh it shall be opened listen I
want you to imagine the scripture in
that very way when you approach the text
when you approach the story ask and it
shall be given you seek look deeper
beyond the surface of the text and you
shall find knock on that text from
various angles keep knocking keep
knocking and God says it'll be open why
because everyone that asks will receive
he that seeks will find and he that
knocks it will be open so those stories
we read in the scriptures those text
where we feel man this text is locked to
me
God says knock and I want you to knock
persistently I want you to seek and
search because the Bible tells us that
if we search for God with all our heart
we will find him
so you're asking okay pastor what do i
do how do I start well it's really very
simple I just want you to start by
reading the word I want you to start by
collecting the pictures of Scripture
read these stories of the Old Testament
and get those stories visualize them I
want you to to sense the story to smell
it to taste it to see it read it as if
you were there and as you begin to
gather these stories in your mind it's
really going to unfold in a very natural
way you see we don't often train our
eyes to view scripture in this way and
that's going to take a little bit of
practice but I want to encourage you
that the more you do this the more you
approach the scriptures looking for the
images looking for the pictures that God
is painting the more powerful your Bible
study is going to be many of us struggle
with the books of Daniel and revelation
the prophecies of daniel and revelation
and let me tell you in reality the books
of Daniel and revelation are full of
pictures and your ability to rightly
understand those books will be in
proportion to your ability to take the
pictures of those books and find their
match in other portions of the scripture
so that's what we're going to do in this
program we are going to teach you how to
find these pictures how to unlock your
eyes so that you can see in a new lines
you know many times after I have
delivered a sermon or preached somewhere
or someone has seen one of my videos or
presentations they'll say to me pastor
I've never seen that in the scripture
before it's as if I'm looking at that
story I'm looking at that verse with new
eyes well that's what photo theology is
photo theology is giving us new eyes and
but either when we begin to see the
scriptures through those new eyes the
scriptures will come alive to us
[Music]
so Elijah's first miracle after leaving
the Jordan after that transition of
power
was that he provided water to the
thirsty it should come as no surprise
that Jesus's first miracle after
crossing the Jordan after returning from
the wilderness was that he went to a
wedding and he turned water to wine
in John to where that story is told the
people at that wedding said the best
wine was saved for last
[Music]
that's what Bible study is
it is turning that which appears to be
plain flavorless
and turning it into the best thing
you've ever tasted or taste and see that
the Lord is good
launched out and I'll see you at the
next episode